Okay, so let's talk about one of the major
components of emotional intelligence,
which is personal skills.
Now remember, personal
skills is about understanding
your own emotions and how
you control your own emotions.
That's where the personal skills section
of emotional intelligence is about.
It's about your own, understanding your
own emotions.
Okay.
Now, there are three components then of
personal skills.
You have self-awareness, self-regulation,
and then there's also motivation.
So these are the three basic components.
So let's talk about each of these.
So it's self-awareness first.
Now self-awareness has three basic skills,
right, or three basic components.
And again, self-awareness is about
yourself, about understanding yourself,
understanding your own
emotions, what triggers
your emotions and so on and stuff off.
or rather understanding what triggers your
emotions.
Now, there's three
components of self-awareness or
three skills that make
up self-awareness, right?
You've got emotional awareness, you've got
self-assessment, and then self-confidence.
So these are the basic three,
self-awareness, or rather, these are the
basic three components of self-awareness,
emotional awareness, self-assessment,
self-confidence.
All right, so let's talk about the first
one, emotional awareness.
So emotional awareness basically refers to
understanding your feelings, knowing
whether you're happy,
sad, angry, and recognizing
how those feelings is going to impact you.
It's going to impact your behavior.
So, again, this is all about understanding
your emotions, how you control yourself,
understanding what triggers your emotions.
So you can see how others see you.
Whether you're happy,
whether you're angry, whether
you're sad, your behavior
can change accordingly.
Other people see that, but do you see
that?
And so can you think objectively,
for example?
So does your emotion impact the workplace?
Does your emotion impact your behavior?
Which it does.
I mean, that's just human nature.
It will do.
But then are you bringing that into the
workplace?
Can you still think objectively when
you're stressful?
Or rather, can you still think objectively
when you're in a stressful environment?
Or when you're, you know, when you're
upset, right, when you're angry or,
you know, when you're sad, can you still
think objectively?
Or, for example, do you only praise your
team members when you're happy?
Your team members are going to know that,
right?
People will recognize your emotions, but
self-awareness is about
recognizing your own emotions.
not recognizing emotions of others,
but recognizing your own emotions.
So that's part of emotional awareness,
right?
First, understanding your emotions.
And then, part of that then, is also
self-assessment, understanding,
perceiving your own strengths and
weaknesses, right?
Understanding what causes your emotions.
So basically then, knowing
your emotional triggers,
knowing what is going to
trigger your emotions, right?
knowing or rather knowing what emotion is
going to trigger your behavior.
Again, others will see that, but do you
see that?
So as a very simple example, I mean,
you know, we all come across this, right?
We're in a group setting, say we're
a group of friends, for example, right?
Or you need team or wherever it is,
you know, you're in a social environment
and, you know, everyone's chatting and
socializing and, you know, happy.
Everyone's getting along, you know,
really, you know, it's just a,
you know, a group of friends or whoever it
is.
And then all of a sudden, somebody gets
really upset, right?
For, you know, smallest thing,
right?
They just suddenly get really upset.
And now that changes the whole mood.
Right, that changes a whole atmosphere,
right, of your group, right?
Just because of one thing.
I'm because of one person.
So understanding what's going to trigger
your emotion is very important.
That's part of self-assessment.
Understanding and knowing how.
to control that and we're going to talk
about that in just a second as well.
And then part of self-awareness is also
self-confidence, being able to express
your opinions, having some kind of
self-esteem, and in fact that developed
self-esteem, self-esteem, being decisive,
taking risk, basically knowing that this
is correct, this decision I'm making is a
correct decision right and so you know you
are being confident there and that's
basically part of self-awareness is
self-confidence right being decisive so
this is one of the components then of
personal skills another component of
personal skills is self-regulation and
self-regulation then refers to
self-composure do you remain cool under
pressure type of thing and basically how
do you respond now to your emotion.
That's really what this is referring to.
And again, people see you how you respond,
but do you know how you respond?
Do you see what people see?
So you can see then there are five
components of self-regulation.
First one is self-control.
So controlling your emotions in a
stressful environment, for example.
So do you remain cool under pressure?
Right?
Are you focused or do you let your
emotions control you?
This is what self-control refers to.
Whether you're happy, whether you're sad,
whether you're angry, right?
So again, how does your emotions actually
impact your behavior?
It's a very simple example.
I mean, how many times you come across a
situation where somebody just sent you
this email and, you know, it's upsetting
you, right?
I mean, whatever they've said or,
you know, it's roughly, your feathers,
you know, you wonder what is this person
talking about, why they're saying this
and, you know, this is all wrong or,
you know, this is inaccurate and,
you know, it's, it's real starts riling
you up.
And so what do you do?
You immediately respond back, right?
You start being, you know, you know,
aggressive and maybe rude and,
uh, yeah, as soon as you hit the send
button, you're like, why did I send that?
Well, that emotion has taken over.
behavior.
So how do you respond to that?
How do you control that?
So maybe next time, you know, I mean,
might not be next time, you know,
you learn over time, but maybe there comes
a point where you decide, okay,
you know, whenever I see an email like
this, that's really upsetting me,
I'm not going to respond back immediately.
I'll wait, right?
I'll wait a few hours or,
you know, well, I'll wait
until the next day, sleep
on it type of thing, right?
Then come back to it think more
objectively.
So that's part of self-control.
Controlling your emotions, right?
Not immediately responding back type of
thing.
Part of self-regulation
then is also trustworthiness,
right, acknowledging your
own errors and mistakes, right?
You have a reputation for honesty,
right?
Moral conduct.
Remember, a leader, right, is always
somebody that people can trust.
Right.
So if you can acknowledge your errors,
people can trust you.
You have a reputation for honesty.
People will trust you.
Right.
So again, we're talking about a good or
bad leader is always subjective.
Right.
So I mean, I'm not
suggesting whether one person
or another person is
a good or a bad leader.
Right.
Everybody, you know, like I said,
that is subjective.
Some people will think a leader is good.
Some people think that same leader is bad.
Right.
So, That's not what we're talking about.
A leader in general, though, will have
many of these traits.
We'll have all or many of these traits.
So trustworthiness, right?
People trust that person.
Then conscientiousness, right,
is another trait, right?
Or another component of self-regulation.
Being organized, right?
Being organized, accountable for your
work.
Again, that goes to trustworthiness.
then you've got adaptability acclimating
to change right now how well do you
respond to change a leader will always
respond to change somebody with emotional
intelligence will always respond to change
by definition a project is a change right
remember the definition of a
project it's temporary temporary
undertaken to create a
unique product service or result.
Unique means it's something different,
something new, something different.
So by definition, since
it's something different to
what we had before or
something new, it's a change.
So by definition a project is a change.
So how well do you respond to change?
So how How well do you acclimate to
change?
So that's part of emotional intelligence.
That's part of self-regulation.
And then a continuation then of change is
innovation.
How do you embrace new ideas?
Do you embrace new ideas?
Fresh new ideas, new
approaches to, you know,
to, and really that's how
the world is changing.
Because we're constantly innovating, we're
constantly finding new
ways of doing things.
So a leader then will always be an
innovator.
A leader will always be a catalyst for
change.
And a leader will always be able to adapt
to change.
So that's self-regulation.
Another skill set then as part of personal
skills is motivation.
What motivates you?
And everybody's motivated differently.
Everybody has different intrinsic factors
to motivate them.
Some people are motivated by money,
some people are motivated by power,
some people are motivated by achievement.
So what motivates you?
So that's what the personal skills or the
motivation section of the
personal skills refers to.
What's your achievement drive?
So this is one of the components
achievement drive.
Remember when we were talking about
McClelland or one of the future videos
we're going to be talking about
McClelland.
So McClellan was basically David
McClelland, he was saying that everybody
has three basic needs, achievement need,
affiliation need, and a power need,
all at varying degrees.
Amongst many, many things,
but in summary, that's one of the
things he was talking about
regarding one of his theories.
So again, coming back here, motivation,
what motivates you?
Is it power?
Is it affiliation with someone?
Is it, you know, what you're trying to
achieve?
So what's your achievement drive?
So that's what this is,
that's what this section
is referring to, establishing
challenging goals.
So you have a goal, you want to achieve
that goal.
And how are you going to work towards that
goal?
Working smartly, working hard to achieve
that goal.
Another part of motivation is commitment.
So again, remember, leadership is all but
collaboration.
As a project manager, you are a leader.
You are leading your team.
right so commitment collaborating with the
team right making sure then you are doing
what it takes to achieve that goal
fulfilling on promises then initiative
going above and beyond to achieve those
goals and inspiring others right so a
leader remember it has influencing skills
part of influencing is also inspiring
others right and then optimism anticipating
success rather than fearing failure.
If you're constantly going to fear
failure, then you're never going to,
you're never going to be successful.
One of the things to always understand,
a leader, right, whenever you've seen
leaders, it's never been a simple cakewalk
for them.
A leader has always had failures in order
to get to the position where they're at,
they've always failed in something or
another.
But emotional intelligence is,
how do you actually react to that failure?
Right.
Do you give up or do you pick yourself up
and continue?
And that's what good leaders have always
done.
They've always had setbacks.
And that's one of the key things about
leadership is how do you respond to failure?
So are you optimistic?
Do you fear failure?
Or do you fear failure?
Or do you anticipate success?
And if you fail, you get up and you
continue.
So are you a glass half full type of
person or a glass half empty?
You should always, a good leader, we'll
always be looking at the glass half full.
They'll always be optimistic.
All right, so these are the components
then of the personal skills, right,
which is one of the major components of
emotional intelligence.